♪
｢there was a hungry crow｣
｢who wanted to get some feed｣
♪
｢if only this beak were longer｣
｢あの餌が もっと
こっちに来れば｣
that feed would be a bit closer
♪
～
｢a crow can think｣
♪
｢can think... can think｣
(
斎藤
)観察し
仮
説を立て
実験をし 考察する｡
Observe, propose a hypothesis, experiment, and then consider.
科学の考え方を学べ｡
Learn the way of scientific thought.
(山本)まずは
｢考える観察｣から｡
We begin with a ｢Thinking Observation｣
今日は 電車の音を観察してみる｡
Today we observe the sounds a train makes.
(電車の音)
この ｶﾞﾀﾝｺﾞﾄﾝという音は
どこで 鳴っているのか｡
This 'click-clack' noise. What's making it?
電車から おりて観察する｡
We obvserve from outside the train.
ここでは ｶﾞﾀﾝｺﾞﾄﾝ鳴っていない｡
The 'click-clack' noise doesn't come from here.
移動
してみる｡
Let's try moving.
(電車の音)
ここでは ｶﾞﾀﾝｺﾞﾄﾝ鳴っている｡
The 'click-clack' noise comes from here.
さっきの場所と
何が ちがうのか？
How is this place different from the last?
２つの場所を くらべてみる｡
Let's try comparing the two places.
ﾚｰﾙに 注目してみると…｡
If we pay close attention to the rails...
こっちには
ﾚｰﾙに 何か付いている｡
Here, there's something attached to the rails.
ここに注目して
音を観察してみる｡
Let's observe the noise while watching this place closely
(電車の音)
車輪が ここを通るたびに…｡
Each time the train wheeels pass here...
(電車の音)
音が
鳴っている｡
We hear the noise.
一体 これは何なのか？
What on earth is this?
よく見てみると…｡
If we look very carefully...
ﾚｰﾙに 切れ目が入っている｡
there's a gap in the rails.
真横から見ると
→
If we look from the side...
すき間が 空いている｡
The crack widens.
この切れ目を 車輪が通る時に
音が鳴っているのか？
Does the sound arise when the train wheels pass over this gap?
(電車の音)
家で 机をずらして
切れ目を作ってみた｡
By shifting a desk, we tried to make such a gap at home.
(切れ目の上を
通る音)
たしかに 鳴った｡
It certainly does make a sound.
♪
～
(
蒼井
)さて 今日は
風船と ﾊﾟｲﾌﾟを使った問題です｡
Well then, today our problem deals with a pipe and some balloons.
ﾊﾟｲﾌﾟの両側に 大きな風船と
小さな風船が 付いていますが
→
On each side of the pipe is a big baloon and a small one.
この２つの風船は
もともと同じ物です｡
These two balloons are the same type.
このﾊﾟｲﾌﾟは
中が 空どうになっています｡
What will happen to the air in this pipe?
でも ここに
弁
が付いていて
中が 仕切られています｡
but here, this valve partitions it.
なので ２つの風船の中の空気は
→
Surely the air in the two balloons
自由に行き来する事が
できません｡
can't move freely between them.
ここを ひねる事で
中の弁が開いて
→
When we twist here, the valve between the two opens
２つの風船の中の空気が
自由に行き来できる事になります｡
the air in the two balloons can then move freely between them.
さて ここからが 問題です｡
Now this is the problem.
この弁を開いた時
→
When I open this valve...
風船は どのように
変化するでしょうか？
How do you think the balloons will change?
１ 大きい風船が さらに ふくらみ
小さい風船は しぼむ｡
1 The large balloon will increase in size further, and the smaller balloon will shrink.
２ 大きい風船が しぼみ
２つの風船が 同じ大きさになる｡
2. The large balloon will shrink and both ballons will assume the same size.
３ このまま 変わらない｡
2. The balloons will remain unchanged.
答えは 番組の最後で発表します｡
We'll reveal the answer at the end of the program.
みなさん 考えておいて下さいね｡
Everyone, please think about it won't you?
♪
～
観察 仮説 実験
そして考察｡
Observation, hypothesis, experiment, and then reflection.
科学の考え方…
Thinking scientifically...
では 先ほどの答えです｡
みなさん ちゃんと考えましたか？
And now the answer to our problem.
Everyone did you think carefully?
１ 大きい風船が さらに ふくらみ
小さい風船は しぼむ｡
1. The larger ballon will grow bigger and the small balloon will shrink.
２ 大きい風船が しぼみ
２つの風船が 同じ大きさになる｡
2. The larger baloon will shrink and both balloons will assume the same size.
３ このまま 変わらない｡
3. They will remain unchanged.
では やってみましょう｡
Well then, let's try it.
風船がどうなるか
よく見ていて下さいね｡
What will happen to the balloons?
Watch carefully, won't you?
(空気の音)
大きい風船は さらに ふくらみ
→
The larger balloon became even larger
小さい風船は
しぼんでしまいました｡
And the smaller balloon shrunk.
もう１回 見てみましょう｡
Let's watch that one more time.
♪
～
答えは
大きい風船が さらに
The answer is that the larger baloon will increase further in size
ふくらみ
→
小さい風船は しぼむでした｡
and the smaller balloon will shrink.
どうしてでしょう｡
Why do you suppose that is?
その ひみつは 風船の中の
空気の あつ力にあります｡
The secret is that inside each balloon there is air pressure.
大きい風船は
中の空気の あつ力が低く…｡
Inside the larger baloon that pressure is lower...
ここから先は 自分で考えよう｡
from here on we think for ourselves.
これからは
みんなが ｢考えるｶﾗｽ｣｡
Now everyone is a thinking crow.